Matheus Vieira Portela

Brasília, DF, Brazil • +55 (61) 99273-9834

http://www.matheusportela.com • http://www.linkedin.com/in/matheusportela http://www.github.com/matheusportela • matheus.v.portela@gmail.com

PROFILE

My dream is to change the world through software and entrepreneurship, creating products that positively impacts millions of people. Aiming for this goal, I have been developing systems and sharpening my leadership skills managing teams both voluntarily and professionally. International experiences include an exchange program to Australia and being the representative of the Brazilian Scouts in Sweden and the United Arab Emirates.

EDUCATION

University of Brasília, Brazil

Mar 2010 – Dec 2015

GPA: 4.21/5

Mechatronics Engineering

Relevant info: Coordinator of a 7 people Robot Soccer Team for two years, assistant director in the most traditional Model UN in Brazil, highest grade in Undergraduate Thesis, honorable mention in Introduction to Game Development class, scholarship holder as Undergraduate Researcher in Robotics.

Australian National University

Jul 2012 – Jul 2013

Exchange Program - Bachelor of Engineering

Science Without Borders program, scholarship holder by the Brazilian government.

Relevant info: Best volleyball player in Bruce Hall, 2nd place as the women's volleyball team coach for Bruce Hall.

EXPERIENCE

Bxblue, Brazil

Feb 2017 – now

Software Developer

• Developing online marketplace for Brazilian citizens to contract payday loans online, removing intermediary services and reducing the time to receive the loan to a few hours, using Ruby on Rails.

University of Brasilia, Brazil

Jan 2017 – now

Temporary Lecturer

- Lecturing Algorithms and Computer Programming for Software Engineering students;
- Supervising 12 Undergraduate Teaching Assistants in helping students and evolving programming skills.

Simbiose Ventures, Brazil

Nov 2015 - Feb 2017

Developer Entrepreneur in Residence

- Recognized as one of the top 4 professionals in the company, out of 15 people, developing
 Machine Learning systems for startups, defining business strategy, creating business canvas
 and marketing strategies;
- Led a 6 people team in developing Machine Learning-powered API for automatic text classification with at most 94% classification accuracy, capable of handling 1M+ requests per month;
- Developed Machine Learning microservice for matching at most 800K products with unstructured data from e-commerces based on state-of-the-art scientific papers and books on Entity Matching;
- Developed system for collecting 140M data points to train Machine Learning model;
- Designed system and scaled it to 400 instances using a distributed Docker approach, messages queues Amazon SQS and Apache Kafka as well as Aerospike NoSQL key-value database;

- Developed business canvas and marketing strategies for 2 products that received seed investments from Silicon Valley-based angel investors;
- Led the Reading Club initiative, being responsible for 45% of the people in Simbiose reading 10 books about business and soft-skills in 6 months.

IPe Network Engineering, Brazil

Jun 2014 – Dec 2014

Intern — Operations and product development

- Developed support software to communicate with third-party Web Application Firewalls using their API, which led the company to acquire the Central Bank of Brazil as a customer;
- Developed vulnerability assessment policies and executed it in enterprise networks with more than 100 active users;
- Started project for automatic detection of web attacks using Python and Machine Learning algorithms based on state-of-the-art scientific papers;
- Analyzed government auctions for network security appliances, such as firewalls, IDS, and WAFs;

CSIRO, Australia Dec 2012 – Feb 2013

Summer Intern — Autonomous systems laboratory

- Developed correction methodology for misrecognized words in speech recognition systems using gaze trackers, 35% faster than usual methods.
- Designed controlled experiments with 20 users, collected and analyzed data.
- Wrote and submitted scientific paper to an international conference.

LANGUAGES

Fluent: Portuguese, English (TOEFL: 108)

Intermediate: French, Spanish

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES

Fluent: Python, C, C++, MATLAB Intermediate: C#, Java, Ruby

Basic: JavaScript, Haskell, LISP, MIPS/x86 Assembly, HTML, CSS

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Frameworks: Django, Rails, Android, jQuery

Libraries: Numpy, Scipy, Scikit-learn, Pandas, Qt, PyQt, SDL, Boost

Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL, Aerospike, Elasticsearch

Others: Machine Learning, Distributed Systems, NoSQL Databases, Robotics

SELECTED PROJECTS AND EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- Scout since 2004, awarded with the Golden Lis Award (highest degree).
- Robot soccer team leader for 2 years, working in all areas 3D Printing, Hardware, Firmware, Communications, Computer Vision and Artificial Intelligence.
- Undergraduate researcher in Robotics and Economics.
- Attended more than 10 Massive Online Open Courses in Computer Science, Economics and Social Sciences at platforms such as Coursera, Udacity, edX and iTunes U.
- Received honorable mention for developing digital game with particle physics simulation, spatial segmentation, and entity system in C++ and SDL.
- Published scientific papers in two international conferences, in Australia and Brazil.